Guide to the Collection of Letters, Receipts, Proofs, Portraits, Etc.
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Collection of letters, receipts, proofs, portraits, etc., concerning The British Gallery of Contemporary Portraits, published by Cadell & Davies
1809-1820
OSBORN FD45
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(2 boxes)
This finding aid is a partial inventory of the contents of Osborn fd45.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a partial inventory of the contents of Osborn fd45. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
Accounting; Biography; Letters; Nobility -- Great Britain; Portraits, British; Publishers and publishing -- England -- London; Great Britain -- Biography -- Portraits; Great Britain -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Cadell, Thomas, 1773-1836; Davies, William, -1820; Picart, Charles, approximately 1780-approximately 1837; Wright, Thomas; Cadell & Davies
- Osborn fd45: Partial List
  - AGAR, JOHN SAMUEL, D. 1835
    - 4 ALS and 1 AL to Cadell and Davies, publishers, 1809-14 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      1809 Sep 7 - 1814 Dec 5
      Stafford Place
      5 p.; various sizes
      About his engravings for the "Gallery
      of Contemporary Portraits".
      fd.45/1-5
  - BARENGER, M.S.
    - Receipt, signed to Cadell and Davies, publishers, 1816 Apr 19 (Box 1)
      n.p.
      1 p.; 9 x 18 cm.
      Payment for engravings.
      fd.45/6
  - CADELL & DAVIES, PUBLISHERS
    - 2 ALS (copies) to William Roscoe (1753-1831), 1808 (Box 1)
      1808 Nov 12 and 1808 Dec 10
      3 p.; 25 x 20 cm.
      Requests him to write the preface for
      the "British Gallery"; sends proofs
      of two of the portraits and plans for
      the rest.
      fd.45/7,8
    - ALS (copy) to Charles Wilkin (1750-1814), 1812 Jan 8 (Box 1)
      Strand
      1 p.; 16 x 16 cm.
      Excuses him from any more work for
      them.
      fd.45/9
  - CARDON, ANTHONY, 1772-1813
    - 5 ALS to Cadell and Davies, publishers, 1809-12 (Box 1)
      1809 Jan 30 - 1812 May 8, and n.d.
      n.p. and London
      8 p.; various sizes
      About his engravings for the "British
      Gallery of Contemporary Portraits".
      fd.45/13-17
  - CHALMERS, ALEXANDER, 1759-1834
    - 3 ALS to Cadell and Davies, publishers, 1808-15 (Box 1)
      1806 Mar 3, 1815 May 19, and n.d.
      4 p.; various sizes
      About the biographies for the
      "British Gallery of Contemporary
      Portraits"; accompanied by a draft
      of a biography in his hand.
      fd.45/10-12
    - 2 ALS to William Davies (d. 1820), n.d. (Box 1)
      3 p.; 20 x 11 cm.
      About his work for the "British
      Gallery of Contemporary Portraits"
      accompanied by 39 biographies for
      the "Gallery" in his hand.
      fd.45/18-59
  - COOK, THOMAS, 1744?-1818
    - AL to William Davies (d. 1820), n.d. (Box 1)
      1 p.; 22 x 19 cm.
      Concerns engravings he has found
      that are "eligible for the British
      Gallery."
      fd.45/104
  - CRAIG, WILLIAM MARSHALL, FL. 1788-1828
    - 3 ALS to Cadell and Davies, publishers, [1809 or later] (Box 1)
      Charlotte St.
      7 p.; 24 x 18 cm. and 20 x 16 cm.
      About his drawings for the "British
      fd.45/60-62
  - DAVIES, WILLIAM, D. 1820
    - ALS to Alexander Chalmers (1759-1834), 1809 Feb 13 (Box 1)
      1 p.; 25 x 20 cm.
      About biographies for Chalmers's
      work for the "British Gallery of
      Contemporary Portraits".
      fd.45/63
  - EDRIDGE, HENRY
    - 2 ALS to [Cadell and Davies, publishers] (Box 1)
      2 p.; various sizes
      About the portraits he is producing
      for the "British Gallery of
      Contemporary Portraits"; accompanied
      by a list of which dignataries'
      portraits have been completed and by
      whom.
      fd.45/64-66
  - EVANS, WILLIAM
    - 2 ALS to Cadell and Davies, publishers, 1808-09 (Box 1)
      1808 Nov 2 and 1809 Mar 8
      Newman St.
      accompanied by 3 receipts from Cadell
      and Davies and 3 signed by Evans to
      Cadell and Davies.
      fd.45/67-71
  - FREEMAN, SAMUEL, 1773-1857
    - AL to Cadell and Davies, publishers, [no yr] Feb 1 (Box 1)
      1 p.; 20 x 12 cm.
      Reports a delay in completing some
      drawings for the "British Gallery of
      fd.45/72
  - GANGAIN, F.
    - ALS to Cadell and Davies, publishers, 1809 Apr 1 (Box 1)
      Chelsea
      1 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      "...if it suited your plan I should
      be glad to serve you in your Galery
      of Portraits..."
      fd.45/73
  - HAUGHTON, MOSES, 1772-1848
    - Receipt, signed, to Cadell and Davies, publishers, 1810 Feb 7 (Box 1)
      2 p.; 8 x 18 cm.
      Payment for drawings done
      accompanied by a receipt from Cadell
      and Davies.
      fd.45/74
  - HOPWOOD, JAMES, 1752?-1819
    - ALS to William Davies (d. 1820), 1809 Mar 18 (Box 1)
      2 p.; 25 x 19 cm.
      mentions Hopwood's son, James Hopwood
      (fl. 1800-1850).
      fd.45/75
  - LANE, WILLIAM, 1746-1819
    - AL to William Davies (d. 1820), 1809 Jan 6 (Box 1)
      2 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      Includes a list of famous people to
      be in the "British Gallery of
      fd.45/76
  - MEYER, HENRY, 1782?-1847
    - ALS to Cadell and Davies, publishers, 1810 Nov 1 (Box 1)
      Gt. Russell Street
      1 p.; 19 x 11 cm.
      Reports on the stage of his
      engravings for the "British Gallery
      of Contemporary Portraits"
      accompanied by 2 receipts from and
      to Cadell and Davies.
      fd.45/77-79
  - MIDDIMAN, SAMUEL, 1750-1831
    - 2 receipts, signed, to Cadell and Davies, publishers, 1815 (Box 1–2)
      1815 May 17 and 1815 Sep 20
      2 p.; 8 x 20 cm.
      Payment received for engravings.
      fd.45/80-81
  - PICART, CHARLES, 1780-1837
    - 15 ALS and 4 AL to Cadell and Davies, publishers, 1809-12 (Box 2)
      1809 Jan 23 - 1812 Dec 31
      28 p.; various sizes
      accompanied by three receipts from
      Cadell and Davies, and 2 receipts,
      signed, to Cadell and Davies; relates
      to Henry Edridge (1769-1821) and
      William Davies (d.1820)
      fd.45/82-102
  - ROLFE, R.
    - ALS to Cadell and Davies, publishers, 1809 Mar 1 (Box 2)
      1 p.; 20 x 14 cm.
      "Gentlemen you shall have the
      portrait of Ed. Coffin in the course
      of a fortnight..."
      fd.45/103
  - SCHIAVONETTI, NICCOLO, 1771-1813
    - 3 ALS to Cadell and Davies, publishers, 1808-09 (Box 2)
      1808 Oct 27, 1809 Jul 18, and n.d.
      Brompton
      accompanied by receipt from Cadell &
      Davies; mentions Francesco Bartolozzi
      (1727-1815).
      fd.45/105-108
  - SCRIVEN, EDWARD, 1775-1841
    - 2 AL to Cadell and Davies, publishers, 1812 (Box 2)
      1812 May 27 and n.d.
      Sommers Town
      About the engravings for the "British
      accompanied by 2 receipts from Cadell
      fd.45/109-112
  - WILKIN, CHARLES, 1750-1814
    - ALS and 2 AL to Cadell and Davies, publishers, 1810-12 (Box 2)
      1812 Dec 9, 1810 Jan 8, and n.d.
      Pimlico and Buckingham Gate
      About work for the "British Gallery
      accompanied by 2 receipts from
      fd.45/113-116
  - WRIGHT, JOHN, D.1820
    - 8 ALS and 2 AL to William Davies (d.1820), 1808-12 (Box 2)
      1808 Aug 16 - 1812 May 5 and n.d
      Burlington Gardens and n.p.
      16 p.; various sizes
      Cadell and Davies and one signed by
      Wright.
      fd.45/117-128